a 2 kilogram tetherball
moves at a speed of 3.5 meters per
second
with a radius of 1.5 meters as shown in
the picture below
what is the angle
that the rope makes with the vertical
and what is the tension force in the
rope
well let's draw a free body diagram
so this ball has a weight force
mg
and it has a tension force
t
now the tension force has an x component
and a y component the x component is t x
the y component is t y
now in this example what provides the
centripetal force
the centripetal force
is the force that keeps the ball
pointed towards the
circle so therefore
t x provides the centripetal force
so we can say t x is equal to fc
t y supports the weight force
so t y
is equal
to mg
in order to calculate the angle
we need to find t x and t y
so let's start with t
y so ty is equal to the mass of 2
kilograms
times the gravitational acceleration
of 9.8 meters per second square
so 2 times 9.8
is 19.6
newtons
so that's ty
tx
is equal to the centripetal force
and we know that the centripetal force
is m v squared divided by r
so therefore t x
is equal to the mass of 2 kilograms
times the speed
of 3.5 meters per second squared
it's meters per second and then you
square it
not meters per second squared like the
units of acceleration just want to
clarify that
and then let's divide this by the radius
of 1.5 meters
so tx
is about 16.33
newtons
so how can we use this information
to find the angle theta
now focus on that particular angle
what trig function
will relate t x and t y is it sine
cosine or tangent
based on sohcahtoa
we need to use the tangent function
tangent is opposite divided by the
adjacent side
so tan theta
is equal to tx
divided by ty
based on the way it's set up
so to find the angle
theta we need to take the arc tangent of
both sides
so theta
is arc tangent or inverse tangent of t x
over t y
so that's going to be arc tan
tx is
16.33
divided by t y
which is 19.6
so the angle theta
is equal to
39.8 degrees
and so that's the answer for part a
now let's move on to part b so i'm gonna
have to
get rid of some stuff
let's get rid of this for now
i'm going to rewrite the values of tx
and ty on top
okay so let's redraw the picture
so this is mg
this is the vertical line
and here we have t x
and t y
our goal
is to calculate the tension force in the
rope
so we can do that now that we have t x
and t y
so
t squared is equal to
t x squared plus t y squared
since this is a right triangle
so t
is just the square root of t x squared
plus t y squared
so that's going to be
square root
16.33 squared
plus
19.6
squared
and so the tension force is
25.51 newtons
and so that's how you can calculate it
so you got to find tx and ty separately
and that will give you the tension force
so let's review the equations that we
had in this video
so when dealing with the tetherball
problem
just remember
tx is equal to the centripetal force
so tx
is mv squared
divided by r
t y supports the weight of the object
so t y
is equal to mg
to find the angle theta
that is
if it's this angle
that's equal to the arc tangent of t x
divided by t y
now let's say for some reason if you
need to find this angle
that angle that's going to be our
tangent t y over t x
so just
make sure you know the difference
between the two hopefully you've taken
trig at this point
and you've mastered the sohcahtoa
concept
now if you need to find t the tension
force is simply equal to the square root
of t x squared plus t y squared
or
if you want to find it directly using
mass and speed
you can also use this equation
so tx is mv squared
over r
and t y is simply just mg
so using the mass of the ball
the speed and the radius
you can find the tension force directly
with this equation
and so this one will give you
the angle that it makes with the
vertical
and so anytime you have a tetherball
problem or anytime an object moves in a
horizontal circle
you can use these equations
but understand this though
if the ball is moving relatively slow
like in this problem
this is what you need to use in order to
calculate the tension
if the ball is moving fast enough
then mg becomes insignificant relative
to mv squared of r
so the tension force you can approximate
it
using
mv squared of r
if the ball
is moving fast enough
if it's moving too slow
and it makes a significant angle you
need to use this equation but if it's
moving fast
where it appears
to be nearly horizontal
then t x is much greater than t y
and so you can approximate t using this
so those are some just some simple
things that you need to keep in mind
when dealing with the tetherball
situation
by the way
what is the period and frequency
of this problem
so given the speed
is 3.5 meters per second
and the radius of the circle
is 1.5 meters with this information
how can you calculate the period
and the frequency
what equation
relates to speed the radius of the
circle and a period
perhaps you've seen this equation before
v is equal to 2 pi r
divided by t now because the ball moves
with constant speed
we have this equation d is equal to v t
and to find v
it's d over t
now because the ball moves in a circle
the distance around a circle is 2 pi r
and the time it takes to complete one
revolution around the circle is the
period
and so that's how we have this equation
so if you want to calculate t
multiply both sides by t
so v t
is equal to 2 pi r
now to get t by itself divide both sides
by v
so the period
is the circumference two pi r
divided by this b
so that's going to be 2 pi
times 1.5 meters
divided by 3.5 meters per second
so the period is about 2.69
seconds
now that we have the period we can
calculate the frequency
so to make one revolution
it takes the ball 2.69 seconds
to do that to make that one revolution
the frequency is one over the period
so it's one over two point six nine
three
that's the next number after the nine
if you round it
so the frequency is going to be about
0.371
hertz
you could also say 0.371
revolutions per second
so that's the frequency
now to calculate the period and
frequency if you know the speed and the
radius of the circle
you